There is an ancient proverb that says
هناك مثل قديم يقول
it's very difficult to find a black cat in a dark room,
أنه من الصعب العثور على قط أسود في غرفة مظلمة،
especially when there is no cat.
خصوصا إذا لم يكن هناك أي قط
I find this a particularly apt description of science
أعتقد أن هذا أفضل وصف للعلم
and how science works --
ولكيفية عمله --
bumbling around in a dark room, bumping into things,
التخبط بالأشياء في غرفة مظلمة،
trying to figure out what shape this might be,
ومحاولة التعرف عليها من أشكالها،
what that might be,
وتخمين ما هي،
there are reports of a cat somewhere around,
هناك تقارير عن قط في مكان ما بالجوار،
they may not be reliable, they may be,
قد تكون المصادر موثوقة أو غير موثوقة
and so forth and so on.
وهكذا دواليك.
Now I know this is different than the way most people
أعلم أن هذا مختلف عن الفكرة الموجودة لدى الناس
think about science.
حول العلم.
Science, we generally are told,
بشكل عام قيل لنا أن العلم
is a very well-ordered mechanism for
هو آلة جد دقيقة من أجل
understanding the world,
فهم العالم،
for gaining facts, for gaining data,
من أجل الحصول على الحقائق، وعلى المعطيات
that it's rule-based,
أن العلم يقوم على قواعد أساسية،
that scientists use this thing called the scientific method
أن العلماء يستعملون ذلك الشيء المسمى بالمنهج العلمي
and we've been doing this for 14 generations or so now,
وأننا نقوم بذلك منذ 14 جيلا وذلك ليومنا هذا،
and the scientific method is a set of rules
والمنهجية العلمية هي مجموعة من القواعد
for getting hard, cold facts out of the data.
تستعمل لاستخراخ حقائق صعبة وجامدة من المعطيات.
I'd like to tell you that's not the case.
أود أن أخبركم بأن الأمور لا تجري بهذا الشكل.
So there's the scientific method,
هناك المنهجية العلمية،
but what's really going on is this. (Laughter)
لكن الذي يحدث في الحقيقة هو هذا. (ضحك)
[The Scientific Method vs. Farting Around]
[المنهجية العلمية مقابل التحرك بغير هدى]
And it's going on kind of like that.
و هذا ما يحدث بشكل ما.
[... in the dark] (Laughter)
[....في الظلام] ( ضحك)
So what is the difference, then,
ما هو الفرق إذن،
between the way I believe science is pursued
بين الطريقة التي أومن بأن العلم يتبعها
and the way it seems to be perceived?
والطريقة التي يبدو بأنها المتبعة؟
So this difference first came to me in some ways
توصلت إلى هذا الاختلاف بشكل ما
in my dual role at Columbia University,
بفضل الدور المزدوج الذي ألعبه في كلية كولومبيا،
where I'm both a professor and run a laboratory in neuroscience
حيث أعمل كأستاذ جامعي وكمدير مختبر في علم الأعصاب
where we try to figure out how the brain works.
حيث نحاول التعرف عن كيفية عمل العقل.
We do this by studying the sense of smell,
نقوم بهذا عن طريق دراسة حاسة الشم،
the sense of olfaction, and in the laboratory,
ويعتبر القيام بهذا العمل في المختبر،
it's a great pleasure and fascinating work
متعة عظيمة وعملا رائعا
and exciting to work with graduate students and post-docs
كما أنه من المثير العمل مع طلبة متخرجين ودكاترة في مرحلة التدريب
and think up cool experiments to understand how this
والتفكير في تجارب مرحة من أجل فهم كيفية
sense of smell works and how the brain might be working,
عمل حاسة الشم وكيف يعمل الدماغ
and, well, frankly, it's kind of exhilarating.
وبصراحة، إنه أمر مبهج.
But at the same time, it's my responsibility
لكن في الوقت نفسه، أنا مسؤول
to teach a large course to undergraduates on the brain,
عن تقديم درس طويل حول الدماغ لطلبة الجامعة،
and that's a big subject,
وهو موضوع كبير،
and it takes quite a while to organize that,
وذلك يحتاج باالتأكيد لوقت من أجل إعداده،
and it's quite challenging and it's quite interesting,
كما أنه تَحَدٍ كبير وجد مهم،
but I have to say, it's not so exhilarating.
لكن يجب علي أن أقول، إنه غير ممتع.
So what was the difference?
فما هو الفرق؟
Well, the course I was and am teaching
يدعى الدرس الذي كنت و مازلت أدرسه
is called Cellular and Molecular Neuroscience - I. (Laughs)
بالعلوم العصبية الجزيئية والخلوية-1. ( ضحك)
It's 25 lectures full of all sorts of facts,
انها 25 محاضرة مليئة بأنواع مختلفة من الحقائق،
it uses this giant book called "Principles of Neural Science"
ويستعمل فيها ذلك الكتاب المشهور والمسمى ''مبادئ علم الأعصاب'
by three famous neuroscientists.
من تأليف ثلاثة علماء أعصاب مشهورين.
This book comes in at 1,414 pages,
و يتكون هذا الكتاب من 1414 صفحة،
it weighs a hefty seven and a half pounds.
و يزن سبعة أرطال ونصف.
Just to put that in some perspective,
وحتى أضعكم في السياق،
that's the weight of two normal human brains.
فإنه يعادل وزن دماغي إنسانين عاديين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I began to realize, by the end of this course,
لذا، مع نهاية هذا الدرس، بدأت أدرك أمرا،
that the students maybe were getting the idea
أنه قد يكون لدى الطلبة تصور
that we must know everything there is to know about the brain.
بأنه علينا فهم كل ما يتعلق بالدماغ.
That's clearly not true.
وهذا أمر غير صحيح على الإطلاق.
And they must also have this idea, I suppose,
وأفترض، بأنهم يعتقدون أيضا،
that what scientists do is collect data and collect facts
بأن دور العلماء هو جمع المعطيات وجمع الحقائق
and stick them in these big books.
وتجميعها في تلك الكتب الضخمة.
And that's not really the case either.
وهذا أيضا ليس بصحيح.
When I go to a meeting, after the meeting day is over
عندما أذهب الى مؤتمر وبعد نهاية فعالياته
and we collect in the bar over a couple of beers with my colleagues,
وخلال اجتماعي بزملائي في المقهى حول الطاولة،
we never talk about what we know.
لا نتحدث أبدا عما نعرفه.
We talk about what we don't know.
نتحدث حول ما لا نعرفه
We talk about what still has to get done,
نتحدث حول ما لم يتم عمله بعد،
what's so critical to get done in the lab.
ما هو الشيء المهم الذي يجب عمله في المختبر.
Indeed, this was, I think, best said by Marie Curie
والحقيقة، أعتقد أن ماري كوري عبرت عن ذلك أفضل مني
who said that one never notices what has been done
حيث قالت يجب على المرء ألا يتحدث أبدا عما أنجز
but only what remains to be done.
بل عما لم ينجز بعد.
This was in a letter to her brother after obtaining
وكان ذلك في رسالة لأخيها بمناسبة حصوله
her second graduate degree, I should say.
على شهادة تخرج ثانية، على ما أعتقد.
I have to point out this has always been one of my favorite pictures of Marie Curie,
يجب أن أقول أن هذه كانت دائما واحدة من صور ماري كوري المفضلة لدي،
because I am convinced that that glow behind her
لأنني مقتنع بأن تلك الهالة المتوهجة خلفها
is not a photographic effect. (Laughter)
ليست تأثيرا فوتوغرافيا. (ضحك)
That's the real thing.
إنه شيء حقيقي.
It is true that her papers are, to this day,
صحيح أن أوراقها مازالت، إلى يومنا هذا،
stored in a basement room in the Bibliothèque Française
مخزنة في غرفة أرضية في المكتبة الفرنسية
in a concrete room that's lead-lined,
في غرفة مبنية من الخرسانة المسلحة،
and if you're a scholar and you want access to these notebooks,
وأنك إذا كنت طالبا وأردت الاطلاع على تلك المذكرات،
you have to put on a full radiation hazmat suit,
فعليك أن ترتدي بذلة كاملةْ الحماية ضد الإشعاعات الخطرة،
so it's pretty scary business.
إنه عمل جد مخيف.
Nonetheless, this is what I think we were leaving out
رغم ذلك، أعتقد أن هذا ما تخلينا عنه
of our courses
في دروسنا
and leaving out of the interaction that we have
وما تخلينا عنه في التفاعل الذي لدينا
with the public as scientists, the what-remains-to-be-done.
مع العامة كعلماء، وهو ما لم ينجز بعد.
This is the stuff that's exhilarating and interesting.
هذا هو الأمر الممتع والمهم.
It is, if you will, the ignorance.
إنه، بكلام واضح، الجهل.
That's what was missing.
إنه الشيء المفقود.
So I thought, well, maybe I should teach a course
فكرت أنه ربما ينبغي علي أن أقوم بإعطاء درس
on ignorance,
حول الجهل،
something I can finally excel at, perhaps, for example.
مادة يمكنني أن أتفوق فيها أخيرا.
So I did start teaching this course on ignorance,
لذا بدأت اقدم دروسا عن الجهل،
and it's been quite interesting
وكان ذلك الأمر جد مثير للاهتمام
and I'd like to tell you to go to the website.
وأود دعوتكم لزيارة موقعي الإلكتروني.
You can find all sorts of information there. It's wide open.
حيث يمكنكم أن تجدوا كل أنواع المعلومات، وهو مجاني بالكامل.
And it's been really quite an interesting time for me
وقد كان بالنسبة لي وقتا جد ممتع
to meet up with other scientists who come in and talk
لالتقاء بعلماء آخرين جاءوا وتحدثوا
about what it is they don't know.
حول ما لا يعرفونه.
Now I use this word "ignorance," of course,
وأستعمل الآن كلمة ''جهل''، بطبيعة الحال،
to be at least in part intentionally provocative,
متعمدا أن أكون مستفزا بشكل ما،
because ignorance has a lot of bad connotations
لأن الجهل يملك الكثير من الدلالات السلبية
and I clearly don't mean any of those.
وبالتأكيد لا أقصد أي من تلك الدلالات.
So I don't mean stupidity, I don't mean a callow indifference
لذا فأنا لا أقصد البلادة، لا أقصد اللامبالاة
to fact or reason or data.
اتجاه الحقيقة أو العقلانية أو المعطيات.
The ignorant are clearly unenlightened, unaware,
والجاهلون هم بالطبع الأشخاص الغير مستنيرين، والغير مدركين
uninformed, and present company today excepted,
والجاهلين، باستثناء الحاضرين هنا اليوم،
often occupy elected offices, it seems to me.
ويبدو لي، أنهم في الغالب يشغلون مناصب مهمة.
That's another story, perhaps.
ربما، أنها قصة أخرى.
I mean a different kind of ignorance.
أنا اقصد نوعا آخر من الجهل .
I mean a kind of ignorance that's less pejorative,
أقصد نوعا من الجهل أقل قدحية،
a kind of ignorance that comes from a communal gap in our knowledge,
نوع من الجهل ناتج عن هوة في معرفتنا المشتركة،
something that's just not there to be known
شيء ليس موجودا لكي يُتَعَرَّفَ عليه
or isn't known well enough yet or we can't make predictions from,
أو لم يعرف بما فيه الكفاية بعد أو لم نستطع أن نتنبأ بشيء من خلاله،
the kind of ignorance that's maybe best summed up
نوع من الجهل قد يكون أفضل وصف له جاء
in a statement by James Clerk Maxwell,
في قولة لجيمس كليرك ماكسويل،
perhaps the greatest physicist between Newton and Einstein,
الذي قد يكون أعظم الفيزيائيين بين نيوتن واينشتاين،
who said, "Thoroughly conscious ignorance
و الذي قال، "الجهل الواعي التام
is the prelude to every real advance in science."
هو مقدمة لكل تقدم حقيقي في مجال العلوم."
I think it's a wonderful idea:
أظن أنها فكرة ممتازة:
thoroughly conscious ignorance.
الجهل الواعي التام.
So that's the kind of ignorance that I want to talk about today,
هذا هو نوع الجهل الذي أردت أن اتحدث عنه اليوم،
but of course the first thing we have to clear up
لكن بطبيعة الحال، أول شيء يجب أن نوضحه
is what are we going to do with all those facts?
هو ما الذي سنفعله بكل تلك الحقائق؟
So it is true that science piles up at an alarming rate.
فما دام العلم مستمرا في التراكم بمعدل ينذر بالخطر.
We all have this sense that science is this mountain of facts,
فسيكون لدينا جميعا ذلك الإحساس بأن العلم هو جبل من الحقائق،
this accumulation model of science, as many have called it,
هذا النموذج التراكمي للعلم، كما سماه الكثيرين،
and it seems impregnable, it seems impossible.
يبدو متماسكا، ومستحيلا.
How can you ever know all of this?
كيف يمكنكم أن تعرفوا كل هذا؟
And indeed, the scientific literature grows at an alarming rate.
والحقيقة، أن الأدب العلمي ينمو بسرعة خطيرة.
In 2006, there were 1.3 million papers published.
ففي 2006، تم نشر 1.3 مليون ورقة بحثية.
There's about a two-and-a-half-percent yearly growth rate,
أي بسرعة نمو تبلغ حوالي 2.5% سنويا،
and so last year we saw over one and a half million papers being published.
وبهذا شهدنا نشر أكثر من 1.5 مليون ورقة بحثية في السنة الماضية.
Divide that by the number of minutes in a year,
لنقسم هذا على عدد الدقائق في السنة،
and you wind up with three new papers per minute.
وستحصلون على ثلاث أوراق بحثية كل دقيقة،
So I've been up here a little over 10 minutes,
إذن، كنت هنا لأكثر من 10 دقائق،
I've already lost three papers.
لقد خسرت ثلاث أوراق.
I have to get out of here actually. I have to go read.
يجب علي الآن أن أخرج من هنا، يجب أن أذهب لأقرأ.
So what do we do about this? Well, the fact is
إذن ماذا يمكن أن نفعله حيال هذا؟
that what scientists do about it is a kind of a controlled neglect, if you will.
الحقيقة هي أن ما يقوم به العلماء حيال ذلك هو نوع من الإهمال المتحكم فيه.
We just don't worry about it, in a way.
فبشكل ما، نحن لا نهتم بها.
The facts are important. You have to know a lot of stuff
الحقائق مهمة. يجب علبكم أن تعرفوا أشياء كثيرة
to be a scientist. That's true.
لتصبحوا علماء. هذه هي الحقيقة.
But knowing a lot of stuff doesn't make you a scientist.
لكن معرفة أشياء كثيرة لن تجعلكم علماء.
You need to know a lot of stuff to be a lawyer
يجب عليكم أن تعرفوا الكثير من الأشياء لتصبحوا محامين
or an accountant or an electrician or a carpenter.
أو محاسبين أو كهربائيين او نجارين.
But in science, knowing a lot of stuff is not the point.
لكن في العلم، معرفة الكثير من الأشياء ليست هي الهدف.
Knowing a lot of stuff is there to help you get
معرفة الكثير من الأشياء يؤدي بك
to more ignorance.
إلى المزيد من الجهل.
So knowledge is a big subject, but I would say
فالمعرفة هي موضوع كبير، لكني أود القول
ignorance is a bigger one.
أن الجهل موضوع أكبر.
So this leads us to maybe think about, a little bit
وهذا ربما يؤدي بنا الى التفكير، قليلا،
about, some of the models of science that we tend to use,
في بعض نماذج العلم التي نرغب في استعمالها،
and I'd like to disabuse you of some of them.
وأود أن أنبهكم إلى بعضها.
So one of them, a popular one, is that scientists
وأحدها، وأشهرها، هو كون العلماء
are patiently putting the pieces of a puzzle together
يضعون بصبر قطع الأحجية بعضها بجانب بعض
to reveal some grand scheme or another.
من أجل استخراج بعض المخططات المهمة أو غيرها.
This is clearly not true. For one, with puzzles,
ومن الواضح أن هذا غير صحيح. لسبب رئيسي،
the manufacturer has guaranteed that there's a solution.
هو أن الشركة المصنعة تضمن بأن هناك حل للأحجية.
We don't have any such guarantee.
بينما نحن ليس لدينا مثل تلك الضمانة.
Indeed, there are many of us who aren't so sure about the manufacturer.
وبالفعل، هناك العديد منا غير متأكد من الشركة المصنعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I think the puzzle model doesn't work.
لذا أظن أن نموذج الأحجية لا يعمل.
Another popular model is that science is busy unraveling things
نموذج آخر يقول بأن العلم مشغول بتفكيك الأشياء
the way you unravel the peels of an onion.
بنفس الطريقة التي تزال بها قشور البصل.
So peel by peel, you take away the layers of the onion
قشرة بعد أخرى، بحيث تبعدون القشرة عن البصلة
to get at some fundamental kernel of truth.
لتصلوا إلى جزء من النواة الأساسية للحقيقة.
I don't think that's the way it works either.
ولا أعتقد بأن هذه هي الطريقة التي يعمل بها أيضا.
Another one, a kind of popular one, is the iceberg idea,
نموذج آخر، مشهور عند الناس، هو فكرة الجبل الجليدي،
that we only see the tip of the iceberg but underneath
الذي لا نرى منه سوى القمة
is where most of the iceberg is hidden.
لكن معظم الجبل الجليدي يختبئ في الأسفل.
But all of these models are based on the idea of a large body of facts
لكن كل هذه النماذج مبنية على فكرة جسم كبير من الحقائق
that we can somehow or another get completed.
التي يمكننا بطريقة أو بأخرى إتمامها.
We can chip away at this iceberg and figure out what it is,
يمكننا أن نكشف عن هذا الجبل الجليدي لنتعرف على ماهيته،
or we could just wait for it to melt, I suppose, these days,
أو يمككنا فقط انتظاره حتى يذوب، بالنظر لما يحدث هذه الأيام،
but one way or another we could get to the whole iceberg. Right?
لكن بطريقة أو بأخرى يمكننا معرفة حجم الجبل الجليدي بالكامل، صحيح؟
Or make it manageable. But I don't think that's the case.
أو التحكم به. لكني لا أعتقد أننا بصدد هذه الحالة.
I think what really happens in science
أعتقد أن ما يحدث بالفعل في العلم
is a model more like the magic well,
هو نموذج أشبه ببئر سحرية
where no matter how many buckets you take out,
حيث لا يهم عدد الدلاء التي يمكنكم إخراجها،
there's always another bucket of water to be had,
فهناك دائما دلو من الماء يجب إخراجه،
or my particularly favorite one,
أو النموذج المفضل لدي،
with the effect and everything, the ripples on a pond.
مع التأثير ومع كل شيء، الأمواج على سطح البركة.
So if you think of knowledge being this ever-expanding ripple on a pond,
إن كنتم تعتقدون بأن المعرفة تكون كتلك الأمواج الدائرية المتسعة على سطح البركة إلى ما لا نهاية،
the important thing to realize is that our ignorance,
الأمر المهم الذي عليكم إدراكه هو أن ذلك هو جهلنا،
the circumference of this knowledge, also grows with knowledge.
فمحيط دائرة تلك المعرفة، ينمو أيضا مع المعرفة.
So the knowledge generates ignorance.
المعرفة تولد الجهل.
This is really well said, I thought, by George Bernard Shaw.
وهذا كلام رائع، في نظري، لجورج برنرد شو.
This is actually part of a toast that he delivered
والحقيقة أنه جزء من الكلمة التي ألقاها
to celebrate Einstein at a dinner celebrating Einstein's work,
في حق أينشتاين خلال حفل عشاء يحتفي بعمله،
in which he claims that science
والتي قال فيها بأن العلم
just creates more questions than it answers. ["Science is always wrong. It never solves a problem without creating 10 more."]
يطرح فقط أسئلة أكثر مما يجيب عنه. ["العلم دائما يخطئ. فهو لا يحل مشكلا دون خلق 10 أخرى."]
I find that kind of glorious, and I think he's precisely right,
وأرى بأنه كلام رائع، وأظن بأنه محق،
plus it's a kind of job security.
كما أنه نوع من الأمن الوظيفي.
As it turns out, he kind of cribbed that
وكما تبين، فإنه نوع من الاقتباس
from the philosopher Immanuel Kant
من القيلسوف إيمانويل كانط
who a hundred years earlier had come up with this idea
الذي جاء منذ القرن الماضي بفكرة
of question propagation, that every answer begets more questions.
السؤال المتفرع، حيث كل جواب يولد المزيد من الأسئلة.
I love that term, "question propagation,"
أحب هذا المصطلح، "السؤال المتفرع،"
this idea of questions propagating out there.
وذاك التصور للسؤال المتفرع.
So I'd say the model we want to take is not
لذلك أود القول بأن النموذج الذي ينبغي علينا الأخذ به
that we start out kind of ignorant and we get some facts together
ليس ذلك الذي ننطلق فيه من أننا جاهلون وبأننا سنحصل على بعض الحقائق معا
and then we gain knowledge.
فنفوز في النهاية بالمعرفة.
It's rather kind of the other way around, really.
في الحقيقة، سيكون الأمر نوعا ما عكس ذلك.
What do we use this knowledge for?
فيما سيفيدنا استخدام تلك المعرفة؟
What are we using this collection of facts for?
فيما سيفيدنا استخدام كل تلك الحقائق المتراكمة لدينا؟
We're using it to make better ignorance,
نحن نستخدمها لصناعة جهل أفضل،
to come up with, if you will, higher-quality ignorance.
وإن شئتم، لابتكار جهل ذو جودة عالية.
Because, you know, there's low-quality ignorance
فكما تعلمون هناك جهل ذو جودة ضعيفة
and there's high-quality ignorance. It's not all the same.
وأخر بجودة عالية. فالجهل يختلف من نوع لآخر.
Scientists argue about this all the time.
ويناقش العلماء هذا الأمر طوال الوقت.
Sometimes we call them bull sessions.
وأحيانا نسميها بمعارك الثيران.
Sometimes we call them grant proposals.
وأحيانا مقترحات المنح.
But nonetheless, it's what the argument is about.
وفي جميع الأحيان، فإن النقاش يدور حول الجهل.
It's the ignorance. It's the what we don't know.
إنه ما لا نعرفه.
It's what makes a good question.
وهو ما يخلق السؤال الجيد.
So how do we think about these questions?
كيف نعمل على إيجاد تلك الأسئلة؟
I'm going to show you a graph that shows up
سأريكم رسم بياني كالذي
quite a bit on happy hour posters in various science departments.
نراه غالبا على الملصقات لدينا في مختلف الأقسام العلمية.
This graph asks the relationship between what you know
ويحاول هذا الرسم البياني الربط بين ما تعرفونه عن أمر ما
and how much you know about it.
وحجم المعرفة التي لديكم عن ذلك الأمر.
So what you know, you can know anywhere from nothing to everything, of course,
فما الذي تعرفونه، قد يبلغ حجم معرفتكم في أي مكان من لاشيء إلى كل شيء
and how much you know about it can be anywhere
ومعرفتكم عن شيء ما قد تتفاوت
from a little to a lot.
من معرفة قليلة إلى كبيرة.
So let's put a point on the graph. There's an undergraduate.
دعونا نضع نقطة على الرسم البياني تمثل طالب سنة أولى.
Doesn't know much but they have a lot of interest.
إنه لا يعرف الكثير لكن لديه اهتمام كبير.
They're interested in almost everything.
وهو مهتم تقريبا بكل شيء.
Now you look at a master's student, a little further along in their education,
الآن أنتم تنظرون إلى طالب ماجستير، سنتقدم قليلا في المشوار الدراسي،
and you see they know a bit more,
وتلاحظون أن معرفته زادت قليلا،
but it's been narrowed somewhat.
لكنها قد ضاقت إلى حد ما.
And finally you get your Ph.D., where it turns out
وفي النهاية تحصلون على الدكتوراه، حيث يتضح
you know a tremendous amount about almost nothing. (Laughter)
بأنكم تعرفون أشياء كثيرة حول تقريبا لا شيء. (ضحك)
What's really disturbing is the trend line that goes through that
الشيء المقلق حقا هو الخط الذي يعبر الرسم البياني
because, of course, when it dips below the zero axis, there,
لأنه، وبالطبع، عندما يغطس الخط دون محور الصفر هناك،
it gets into a negative area.
فإنه يدخل المنطقة السلبية.
That's where you find people like me, I'm afraid.
وهو المكان الذي تجدون فيه أشخاص مثلي، أنا خائف.
So the important thing here is that this can all be changed.
الشيء المهم هنا هو أن ذلك الأمر قابل للتغيير.
This whole view can be changed
كل هذا المشهد قابل للتغيير
by just changing the label on the x-axis.
وذلك عن طريق تغيير تسمية المحورسيني فقط.
So instead of how much you know about it,
بدلا من التساؤل عن حجم معرفتكم بشيء ما،
we could say, "What can you ask about it?"
يمكننا طرح السؤال التالي: "ما هو السؤال الذي يمكنكم طرحه بشأن امر ما؟"
So yes, you do need to know a lot of stuff as a scientist,
وبالطبع أنتم بحاجة لمعرفة الكثير من الأشياء كما هو حال العلماء،
but the purpose of knowing a lot of stuff
لكن الهدف من معرفة الكثير من الأشياء
is not just to know a lot of stuff. That just makes you a geek, right?
ليست هي الغاية. فهي فقط تجعلكم أكثر هوسا، صحيح؟
Knowing a lot of stuff, the purpose is
معرفة الكثير من الأشياء، الهدف هو
to be able to ask lots of questions,
أن تكونوا قادرين على طرح الكثير من الأسئلة،
to be able to frame thoughtful, interesting questions,
وقادرين على طرح أسئلة مدروسة ومثيرة للاهتمام،
because that's where the real work is.
لأن تلك هي النقطة التي يجب العمل عليها.
Let me give you a quick idea of a couple of these sorts of questions.
دعوني أريكم بضعة أفكار سريعة عن ماهية تلك الأسئلة.
I'm a neuroscientist, so how would we come up
أنا عالم أعصاب، فكيف يمكننا أن نخرج
with a question in neuroscience?
بسؤال جاد في علم الأعصاب؟
Because it's not always quite so straightforward.
لأن الأمر ليس دائم السهولة.
So, for example, we could say, well what is it that the brain does?
على سبيل المثال، يمكننا القول: "ما الذي يفعله الدماغ؟"
Well, one thing the brain does, it moves us around.
من الأمور التي يقوم بها الدماغ، جعلنا نتحرك.
We walk around on two legs.
نحن نمشي على قدمين.
That seems kind of simple, somehow or another.
بشكل أو بأخر، يبدو هذا الأمر بسيطا.
I mean, virtually everybody over 10 months of age
أقصد أن كل شخص عمره أكثر من 10 أشهر
walks around on two legs, right?
يمشي على رجلين، صحيح؟
So that maybe is not that interesting.
قد لا يكون هذا الأمر مثير للاهتمام.
So instead maybe we want to choose something a little more complicated to look at.
بدلا من ذلك قد نكون بحاجة لاختيار شيء أكثر تعقيدا بقليل لنحلله.
How about the visual system?
ماذا عن النظام البصري؟
There it is, the visual system.
هذا هو، النظام البصري.
I mean, we love our visual systems. We do all kinds of cool stuff.
أعني، نحن نحب نظامنا البصري. إنه يساعدنا جميعا في القيام بأشياء مثيرة.
Indeed, there are over 12,000 neuroscientists
في الواقع، هناك أزيد من 12,000 عالم أعصاب
who work on the visual system,
يعمل على النظام البصري،
from the retina to the visual cortex,
انطلاقا من الشبكية حتى القشرة البصرية،
in an attempt to understand not just the visual system
في محاولة ليس لفهم النظام البصري وحسب
but to also understand how general principles
بل أيضا لفهم المبادئ العامة
of how the brain might work.
التي قد يكون الدماغ يعمل بها.
But now here's the thing:
لكن يبقى الإشكال هو:
Our technology has actually been pretty good
أنه لدينا تكنولوجيا جيدة
at replicating what the visual system does.
في تقليد ما يفعله النظام البصري.
We have TV, we have movies,
لدينا التلفاز والأفلام
we have animation, we have photography,
والرسوم المتحركة والتصوير
we have pattern recognition, all of these sorts of things.
والتعرف على الأنماط، وكل ما يشبه ذلك.
They work differently than our visual systems in some cases,
وهي نوعا ما تعمل بشكل مختلف عن نظامنا البصري،
but nonetheless we've been pretty good at
لكن رغم ذلك فقد قمنا بعمل جيد
making a technology work like our visual system.
في جعل التكنولوجيا تعمل كنظامنا البصري.
Somehow or another, a hundred years of robotics,
إلا أنه وخلال مئات السنين من العمل على الرجال الآليين،
you never saw a robot walk on two legs,
لم تشاهدوا قط رجل آلي يمشي على قدمين،
because robots don't walk on two legs
لأن الرجال الآليين لا يمشون على قدمين
because it's not such an easy thing to do.
ولأنه ليس عملا يسهل القيام به.
A hundred years of robotics,
المئات من السنين من العمل على الرجال الآليين،
and we can't get a robot that can move more than a couple steps one way or the other.
ولم نتمكن من جعل رجل آلي يقوم ببضع خطوات ذهابا وإيابا.
You ask them to go up an inclined plane, and they fall over.
وعندما تجعلونهم يمشون على سطح مائل يسقطون للخلف.
Turn around, and they fall over. It's a serious problem.
وعندما يدورون حول أنفسهم يسقطون. إنه مشكل عويص.
So what is it that's the most difficult thing for a brain to do?
فما الأمر الأكثر صعوبة الذي يقوم به الدماغ؟
What ought we to be studying?
وما الذي يجب علينا دراسته؟
Perhaps it ought to be walking on two legs, or the motor system.
ربما كان يجب دراسة المشي على القدمين، أو الجهاز الحركي.
I'll give you an example from my own lab,
سأقدم لكم مثالا من مختبري،
my own particularly smelly question,
سؤالي ذو الرائحة،
since we work on the sense of smell.
منذ أن بدأنا في العمل على حاسة الشم.
But here's a diagram of five molecules
هذا رسم بياني لخمس جزيئات
and sort of a chemical notation.
وهو نوع من الترميز الكيميائي.
These are just plain old molecules, but if you sniff those molecules
إنها مجرد جزيئات عادية، لكن إذا شمها أحدكم
up these two little holes in the front of your face,
عن طريق عضو الشم على وجوهكم،
you will have in your mind the distinct impression of a rose.
سيرسم في أذهانكم انطباع على أنها وردة.
If there's a real rose there, those molecules will be the ones,
وإن لم يكن هناك من وردة، فإن تلك الجزيئلت ستكون منها،
but even if there's no rose there,
لكن حتى وإن لم يكن هناك من ورد،
you'll have the memory of a molecule.
سيصبح لديكم ذكرى عن جزيء.
How do we turn molecules into perceptions?
كيف نحول الجزيئات إلى إدراكات ذهنية؟
What's the process by which that could happen?
ما هي العملية التي يمكن من خلالها حدوث ذلك؟
Here's another example: two very simple molecules, again in this kind of chemical notation.
هذا مثال أخر: جزيئين عاديين، في هذا الترميز الكيميائي.
It might be easier to visualize them this way,
قد يكو من الأسهل تصورهما بهذا الشكل.
so the gray circles are carbon atoms, the white ones
الدوائر الرمادية هي ذرات الكربون والبيضاء
are hydrogen atoms and the red ones are oxygen atoms.
ذرات الهيدروجين والحمراء ذرات الأوكسجين.
Now these two molecules differ by only one carbon atom
يختلف هذين الجزيئين في ذرة كربون واحدة فقط
and two little hydrogen atoms that ride along with it,
وذرتي الهيدروجين الصغيرتين المركبة معها،
and yet one of them, heptyl acetate,
ومع ذلك فإن واحدة منهما، الهيبتيل أسيتات،
has the distinct odor of a pear,
له تلك الرائحة المميزة للأجاص،
and hexyl acetate is unmistakably banana.
بينما الهيكسيل أسيتات له رائحة الموز.
So there are two really interesting questions here, it seems to me.
في رأيي يبدو أن هناك سؤالين جد مثيرين،
One is, how can a simple little molecule like that
أولا، كيف يمكن لجزيء صغير كهذا
create a perception in your brain that's so clear
من خلق إدراك بهذا الوضوح في ذهنكم
as a pear or a banana?
بإجاصة أو موزة؟
And secondly, how the hell can we tell the difference
ثانيا، كيف يمكننا أن نفرق بين جزيئين
between two molecules that differ by a single carbon atom?
لا يختلفان سوى بذرة كربون واحدة فقط؟
I mean, that's remarkable to me,
أعني، هذا أمر مدهش في نظري،
clearly the best chemical detector on the face of the planet.
هذا بلا منازع أفضل كاشف كيميائي على وجه الأرض.
And you don't even think about it, do you?
وأنتم لم تفكروا حتى بذلك، هل فعلتم؟
So this is a favorite quote of mine that takes us
ستأخذنا هذه المقولة المفضلة عندي
back to the ignorance and the idea of questions.
للوراء نحو الجهل وفكرة الأسئلة الجادة.
I like to quote because I think dead people
وأنا أحب الاقتباس لأني أعتقد بأنه علينا
shouldn't be excluded from the conversation.
ألا نقصي الأشخاص الذين سبقونا من الحوار.
And I also think it's important to realize that
وبالمناسبة، أعتقد أيضا بأنه من المهم أن ندرك بأن
the conversation's been going on for a while, by the way.
هذا الحوار قد انطلق منذ مدة.
So Erwin Schrodinger, a great quantum physicist
فقد أشار إرفين شرودنغر، وهو فيزيائي عظيم في الكم
and, I think, philosopher, points out how you have to
وفيلسوف حسب رأيي، إلى الطريقة التي يجب عليكم
"abide by ignorance for an indefinite period" of time.
"تقبل الجهل لمدة غير محددة" من الوقت.
And it's this abiding by ignorance
وأعتقد أن هذا التقبل للجهل
that I think we have to learn how to do.
هو ما يجب علينا تعلمه.
This is a tricky thing. This is not such an easy business.
إنه أمر معقد. ذلك ليس بالعمل السهل.
I guess it comes down to our education system,
أظن أن ذلك يقوم على نظامنا التعليمي،
so I'm going to talk a little bit about ignorance and education,
لذا سأتحدث قليلا عن الجهل والتعليم،
because I think that's where it really has to play out.
لأني أعتقد بأنها النقطة التي يجب العمل عليها.
So for one, let's face it,
لذا دعونا نواجه الأمر مرة واحدة،
in the age of Google and Wikipedia,
ففي عصر جوجل وويكيبيديا،
the business model of the university
فإن النماذج التي لدينا من الجامعات
and probably secondary schools is simply going to have to change.
وربما حتى الثانويات تتجه نحو التغيير.
We just can't sell facts for a living anymore.
لم يعد بإمكاننا العيش على بيع الحقائق بعد اليوم.
They're available with a click of the mouse,
فقد أصبحت متاحة بكبسة زر، أو بشكل واضح،
or if you want to, you could probably just ask the wall
ربما يمكنكم فقط سؤال الجدار
one of these days, wherever they're going to hide the things
في يوم ما، أينما كانوا سيخبئون الأشياء
that tell us all this stuff.
التي ستخبرني بكل هذه الأمور.
So what do we have to do? We have to give our students
فما الذي علينا القيام به؟ علينا أن نجعل طلابنا يتذوقون طعم المغامرة،
a taste for the boundaries, for what's outside that circumference,
لما يوجد خارج الدائرة،
for what's outside the facts, what's just beyond the facts.
لما يوجد خارج الحقائق، لما يختبئ خلف الحقائق.
How do we do that?
فكيف نقوم بذلك؟
Well, one of the problems, of course,
وبطبيعة الحال، فإن واحدة من المشاكل
turns out to be testing.
تتمثل في الاختبارات.
We currently have an educational system
نملك اليوم نظام تعليمي جد فعال
which is very efficient but is very efficient at a rather bad thing.
لكنه جد فعال في إنتاج أشياء سيئة نوعا ما.
So in second grade, all the kids are interested in science,
في المستوى الثاني، جميع الأطفال مهتمين بالعلوم،
the girls and the boys.
بنات وبنين.
They like to take stuff apart. They have great curiosity.
لأنهم يحبون تفكيك الأشياء. لأن لديهم فضول كبير.
They like to investigate things. They go to science museums.
ويحبون البحث في الأشياء. ويذهبون إلى المتاحف العلمية.
They like to play around. They're in second grade.
ويحبون اللعب. إنهم في المستوى الثاني.
They're interested.
إنهم مهتمون بكل شيء.
But by 11th or 12th grade, fewer than 10 percent
لكن في المستوى الثانوي، أقل من 10 بالمائة منهم
of them have any interest in science whatsoever,
يُظْهِر بعض الاهتمام بالعلوم،
let alone a desire to go into science as a career.
ناهيك عن الرغبة في خوض غمار العمل العلمي.
So we have this remarkably efficient system
لدينا هذا النظام العالي الكفاءة
for beating any interest in science out of everybody's head.
في القضاء على أي اهتمام بالعلوم يظهره أي أحد.
Is this what we want?
هل هذا ما نريده حقا؟
I think this comes from what a teacher colleague of mine
أعتقد أن هذا نتاج ما يسميه أحد زملائي الأساتذة
calls "the bulimic method of education."
ب "الطريقة النهمة للتعليم"
You know. You can imagine what it is.
تعلمون عما أتحدث.
We just jam a whole bunch of facts down their throats over here
حيث نحشوهم بمجموعة من الحقائق من جهة
and then they puke it up on an exam over here
ليتقيؤوها بعد ذلك في الامتحان من جهة أخرى
and everybody goes home with no added intellectual heft whatsoever.
بحيث يعودون للمنزل دون أية إضافة فكرية.
This can't possibly continue to go on.
لا يمكن لهذا الحال أن يستمر.
So what do we do? Well the geneticists, I have to say,
ماذا نفعل؟ علي القول بأن علماء الوراثة
have an interesting maxim they live by.
يَتَّبِعُون مثلا مثيرا.
Geneticists always say, you always get what you screen for.
يقول علماء الوراثة دائما: "أنت تجد ما تبحث عنه"
And that's meant as a warning.
وهو في نظرهم تحذير.
So we always will get what we screen for,
نحن دائما نجد ما نبحث عنه،
and part of what we screen for is in our testing methods.
وجزء مما نبحث عنه هو في طريقتنا في الامتحان.
Well, we hear a lot about testing and evaluation,
سمعنا الكثير حول الفرق بين الامتحان والتقييم،
and we have to think carefully when we're testing
لذا يجب علينا التفكير بتأني عتدما نمتحن
whether we're evaluating or whether we're weeding,
ما إذا كنا نقيم أو نزيل الأعشاب الضارة،
whether we're weeding people out,
أم أننا نزيل الأشخاص الضارين،
whether we're making some cut.
أو نُقَلِّم بعض الشيء.
Evaluation is one thing. You hear a lot about evaluation
التقييم هو شيء واحد فقط. سمعتم الكثير حول التقييم
in the literature these days, in the educational literature,
في الأدبيات التربوية في هذه الأيام،
but evaluation really amounts to feedback and it amounts
لكن التقييم يرجع في الحقيقة للمراجعة
to an opportunity for trial and error.
والفرصة في التجريب والخطأ.
It amounts to a chance to work over a longer period of time
إنه يرجع لفرصة للعمل مع هذا النوع من المراجعة
with this kind of feedback.
على المدى البعيد.
That's different than weeding, and usually, I have to tell you,
إنه يختلف عن إزالة الأعشاب الضارة، وعلي إخباركم، أنه في العادة،
when people talk about evaluation, evaluating students,
عندما يتحدث الناس عن التقييم، يقيمون الطلبة
evaluating teachers, evaluating schools,
ويقيمون المدرسين ويقيمون المدارس
evaluating programs, that they're really talking about weeding.
ويقيمون البرامج، إنهم يتحدثون في الحقيقة عن إزالة الأعشاب الضارة.
And that's a bad thing, because then you will get what you select for,
وهذا أمر سيء، لأنكم ستحصلون بعدها عما اخترتم،
which is what we've gotten so far.
وهذا ما حصلنا عليه لحد الآن.
So I'd say what we need is a test that says, "What is x?"
أود القول بأننا بحاجة لامتحان يكون السؤال فيه: " ما هو إكس؟"
and the answers are "I don't know, because no one does,"
ويكون الجواب: " لا أعلم، لأنه لا أحد يعلم"
or "What's the question?" Even better.
أو أفضل من ذلك "ما هو السؤال؟".
Or, "You know what, I'll look it up, I'll ask someone,
أو "لحظة، سأبحث وأجيب، سأسأل أحدهم،
I'll phone someone. I'll find out."
سأتصل بأحدهم. سأجد الجواب."
Because that's what we want people to do,
لأن هذا ما نريد من الناس فعله،
and that's how you evaluate them.
وبهذه الطريقة تقيمونهم.
And maybe for the advanced placement classes,
أما بالنسبة للأقسام المتقدمة قد يكون الأمر
it could be, "Here's the answer. What's the next question?"
كما يلي، "هاكم السؤال. فما هو السؤال التالي؟"
That's the one I like in particular.
وهو أكثر شيء أفضله.
So let me end with a quote from William Butler Yeats,
دعوني أنهي بقولة لويليام بتلر ييتس،
who said "Education is not about filling buckets;
الذي قال: "أن تُعَلِّمَ لا يعني أن تملأ الدلاء
it is lighting fires."
بل أن تشعل نيران."
So I'd say, let's get out the matches.
في النهاية أود القول، فلنخرج عيدان الثقاب.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)